So thank you for having me.
So this is called “From Voice
to Environment: Authorship
in Spatial Collage.”
My name is Dan Lichtman.
I'm an assistant professor at Saint John's
University in New York City.
I teach game development
and emerging media.
So I'm going to present today— Actually,
I want to keep track of time.
I'm going to present
about a project of mine called a Community
Game Development Toolkit, and I'm going to
show example projects from this toolkit.
And then I'm going to talk at the end
a little bit about themes of authorship
that I think, you know, can be reflected
on as a result of these projects.
So the Community Game Development
Toolkit is a— hold on one second.
Let me try to— My preview of all
your faces is covering up my slide.
So. This is an accessible
collage based system for collective game
making.
It's open to diverse participants
and ways of making,
and it supports communities
to represent their own stories
and knowledge.
Are you— sorry, I can't see chat
or anything or hear anything
when I'm sharing my slides apparently.
You guys still see—
Yeah, we can see this way.
You do?
Okay, cool.
All right. Thanks.
I will continue with confidence.
Okay, so this is a summary
of the Community Game Development Toolkit.
So the Community Game Development
Toolkit is a system that works
in the Unity game engine,
which if you're not familiar with it, it's
a big commercial game engine
for making interactive experiences.
And the toolkit— in one of the main things
it does
is simplify how you use it,
because it's a pretty complex,
intimidating piece of software,
but it has a real focus on collage.
So the kinds of source materials
that people use might include
drawings and paintings,
photographic cutouts.
And then in the lower left
I have a 3D scan.
So you can also
easily make 3D scans with any smartphone
now and incorporate those
into collages in 3D space.
So what do you do with those materials?
You bring them into the game engine.
So here I have an example.
And you arrange them in a 3D space
and you can kind of position and rotate
and scale each object.
Here I have some scans of drawings
and also a
skybox, which is like a 360 degree photo
that forms the background
and you form these
into navigable environments.
So what the toolkit does is
it makes this really complex piece
of software much more approachable
through this lens of collage,
and it abstracts away
quite a bit of the interface.
And also you don't have to do any coding
when you use this
when you use this system.
So I'm going to show you
some example projects.
This is called “In the Middle”
and in this project— used the toolkit
as a shared platform for worldbuilding.
So in this project,
I worked with some collaborators
at the University of Nebraska in Lincoln,
and we worked
with community members in rural Nebraska,
in the panhandle of Nebraska.
And one of the main communities
that we worked with were people
that are affected
by substance use disorder.
And we created a series
of game-like worlds, which I'm
going to show you, and I'll tell you
about the process of how we made them.
So in
this project, community members
participated in worldbuilding sessions.
So these were kind of structured
but open ended discussion and drawing
and ideation sessions
where community members
imagined speculative futures
in which the environment
and the social infrastructure
and the community and
the city and town
and all the services around them
would better serve the needs, particularly
of people affected by and recovering
from substance use disorders.
So they imagine technologies,
social systems, civic systems
that would make people feel supported,
support their recovery,
enhance community engagement,
enhance feeling connected to community.
And then we worked with collage.
So you can see here this is a
this is a video
recording of a interactive scene.
And the scene consists of 3D
scans of objects, photos of objects,
photo cutouts.
The ground is a series of textures
that were either
photographed or 3D scanned.
And there's objects that are 3D scanned.
So this is a collage.
It's kind of visually abstract,
but it's very much grounded in
embodied experience of kind of a cultural,
geographic and political landscape.
Here's another recording.
The animal care robot is designed
as a versatile solution for pet owners
with diverse needs, focusing on enhancing
pet care through advanced functionality.
It monitors biometric levels,
emotions, and basic needs.
The animal care role— Okay,
so what you just heard
was that embedded in these scenes,
there are recordings of the speculative
ideas that
the community members
created during the worldbuilding sessions.
So as you navigate the scene,
you can approach
these interactive animations
and hear about the ideas
that— the speculative ideas
about this preferable future.
And then lastly, for this project,
there are—
we created some interactive features,
such as leaving in-scene voice notes.
So if you're navigating the scene,
if you're a participant
or a community member,
you can leave a voice note in the space
and other people can listen to it.
So this is a way of building
kind of asynchronous dialog and discourse
within the community.
And you can even vote on the ideas,
which ideas you think are interesting,
which ideas should receive support.
So in total, this kind of leads to like
a living distributed community archive.
So second example project
that I want to show you is “Blanket Forts
and Other Assemblages.”
This is a special issue
of the journal Hyperrhiz:
New Media Cultures.
So this is a special issue
that myself and a few other people,
listed on the slide—Catalina
Alvarez, Sue Huang, Lee Tusman—
we co-edited this special issue
and participants— contributors
created projects with the Toolkit,
so that among the themes of the issue
was that
the projects were inspired by the idea
of the houseboat, the campsite,
the terrarium, and the diorama.
So these are kind of ad hoc dwellings
or dwellings that are created
piecemeal, and they may be temporary
and they're fragmented.
And a lot of the projects
explored new modalities of intimacy
and collectivity, and also imagined
how fragments of the past
could contribute
to thinking about possible futures. So.
In one example project,
Camille Intson created “Bisexual Bedroom
Imaginaries.”
So she used a series
of a 360 degree photo, a series of photo
cutouts, and a number of 3D scans
to kind of create
this memory
speculative version of her
teenage bedroom, kind of past—
a memory of the past,
but also projected it into the future
of this space where the creator
kind of came into an understanding
of their own sexual identity.
And then on the right
we have Bahareh Khoshooee.
And this scene
is called “Thoughts and Prayers
from a Glowing Rectangle.”
And in this project,
the author was imagining
spaces of diaspora and spaces of grief
and intergenerational grief.
And you can navigate the environment
and read and hear
recordings
and quotations from family members of the
author from different generations
amidst this kind of visually abstract
environment.
All right. So.
“Workshops at the Queens Library.”
So this is something
I've been working on recently
and I'm currently working on.
So this took the tool that came Community
Game Development
Toolkit into a public civic context.
It was workshops with teens,
and the teens made stories
about their own lives
and their own community
and their own culture using 3D collage,
using the Toolkit.
So they were each—
there's been two two series of workshops
so far, and each one had two two-hour
long sessions.
And the general format was that the
first session, we introduced the Toolkit,
and then later,
so that students would understand
how to use the game environment,
how to bring assets into the environment.
Had I composed and arranged them,
and then later in the first session,
we would talk about
the kind of creative exercise
of reflecting on participants’ own
lives and homes and families
and social networks and communities.
And their homework
was to create a kind of archive
and gather materials
to create their own environment.
And then in the second workshop,
they would bring these materials in
and they would work on their own projects.
So this had a lot of—
there was a lot of challenges in this,
in this project, which were
really interesting to work through.
One was that,
you know, if you've ever worked with
big public institutions, you probably know
that it's— there's a lot of bureaucracy,
there's a lot of people involved.
And just getting, you know, getting things
set up is a big undertaking.
And then with this, there's
also a lot of technical infrastructure
that was involved.
So I got the IT department at
my university, provided all the computers.
And to make it really as accessible
as possible,
we set up an example project
and so that it would be
you could basically turn on the computer
and it would be ready to go.
I see something in the chat maybe.
About two minutes left.
Okay.
So one technology
that I kind of developed for this,
for this workshop that overcame
some of these challenges was
that it was really hard to get materials
from people's phones to these laptops.
So I made a web based system
where on the phone,
people can take their picture
and upload it.
It would mask out the background
by itself, and then they could download it
just through the web
with a special code on their computer.
Okay.
So I'll use my last two minutes
to talk about authorship
a little bit.
How is authorship distributed across
the making and readings of these worlds?
So I'm going to talk about gathering,
composing, and navigating.
So if you think about traditional
collage— So Benesch has written
a book called “Collage Culture.”
In traditional collage, meaning no longer
resides in a stable composition organized
around a central point of view, but
emerges through relations among fragments.
I think most people who are familiar
with collage
have thought about these kinds of ideas.
Collage unsettles
the idea of a unified subject position,
suggesting
instead that perception and experience
are assembled from partial, heterogeneous,
and often conflicting elements.
So in this 3D version of collage
that participants make,
they work with found photographs
and family photographs, Internet images,
all kinds of materials, and the materials
are gathered through lived experience.
So that's one thing that I think
makes this process unique
compared
to more traditional forms of collage,
is that most material
that people work with is coming
from their own life and community.
The archive that people are working with,
often they create during the project.
They're not working with established
archives
like a library or a newspaper in general.
And sometimes the archive, for example,
like in the Nebraska Project, is
collectively produced. So.
Composing is a second phase.
So in the process of composing,
you add an image, you walk around,
you test it, you navigate it,
you scan something else,
you change a scale, you rotate,
you revisit things.
So during the composing process,
the author inhabits the world.
The author is switching roles
between maker and viewer,
and the author makes
and remakes an environment.
So in a way, I would say that
the author in this case composes
relations and meaning emerges
through process and exploration.
And this relates to Ingold,
who says that making can be understood
as a process of wayfinding, which form
and meaning arise through engagement
in materials, rather through the execution
of a predefined plan.
So one thing— I'm going to wrap up in
just a second.
So one thing that I find
really interesting about this process
is that the storytelling aspect
of these visual worlds is really emergent.
So almost nobody has a preexisting plan.
Or even if they do,
they get led in different directions
as they compose the relationships
between the objects in the 3D space
and then finally navigating.
So if you're the viewer, you walk,
you turn your approach, you enter,
and in the process, you might notice
and discover and compare and revisit.
Narrative emerges through navigation.
The author composes relationships
and the reader composes narratives.
So it's almost as though the author is
composing a space where
relationships and associations
and meanings can occur.
And then the reader kind of completes
this space by choosing their own path
through this space.
And so this relates to Murray’s
“Hamlet on the Holodeck,”
which talks about digital environments
and procedural—you know,
the procedural formation of environments
that— participatory narrative.
So she was talking about hypertext,
but I think some of the same ideas
apply to this
aspect of interactive narrative.
So I will leave it there.
I think I'm out of time.
There's been a number of
exhibitions and articles
that were written about this.
Thank you very much.
That's my website.
That's the community website.
That's my email address.
Hope to talk to some of you guys soon.